A guide to the Benjamin E. Washburn papers FA038
Rockefeller Archive Center
Benjamin E. Washburn papers
1905-1960, 1913-1939
Rockefeller Archive Center
Washburn, Benjamin Earle
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
FA038
3.5 Cubic Feet 4 document cases
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research without restrictions.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 13
Biographical / Historical
A physician, public health officer, and author, Benjamin E. Washburn was born in Rutherford County, North Carolina, in 1885. Dr. Washburn received undergraduate (1906) and graduate (1909) degrees in English and history from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and graduated from the University of Virginia in 1911 with a degree in medicine. It was during his internship in Wilmington, North Carolina, that he met Zillah Howe, a nurse from Michigan, whom he married October 6, 1912.
Following a brief private practice in Rutherford County, North Carolina, Dr. Washburn began his long connection with Rockefeller organizations as an employee of the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission. As field director for Haywood, Stanley, and Caswell counties in North Carolina, he led a hookworm eradication campaign; he later (May-December 1914) became a full-time health officer in Nash County, North Carolina, as part of a program of community sanitary work funded by The Rockefeller Foundation.
In 1915 Dr. Washburn was appointed field director for the International Health Commission's campaign for control of hookworm in British Guiana and Trinidad. Returning to North Carolina in 1916, Washburn, as county health officer in Wilson County, developed a program of health work intended to serve as a model for other counties and as a training center for International Health Board field staff. In 1917, Dr. Washburn was appointed director of the new state Bureau of County Health Work where he was responsible for the creation of cooperative health programs in ten North Carolina counties.
Dr. Washburn left North Carolina again in 1930 to direct the IHB's Hookworm Campaign in Jamaica and remained to inaugurate and oversee the Malaria Campaign, the Tuberculosis Commission, and the Bureau of Health Education. In 1935, he was appointed regional director for the International Health Division in the West Indies and Central America. Washburn retired from The Rockefeller Foundation in 1939.
Upon retirement, Washburn returned to Rutherfordton, North Carolina, where he was active in state and local public health affairs. He also served as health editor for the Raleigh, North Carolina, "Progressive Farmer" from 1940 to 1951 and wrote several books devoted to his health interests.
Dr. Washburn is the author of "Jamaica Health Stories and Plays" (1929); "The Health Game" (1930); "A Country Doctor in the South Mountains" (1955); "As I Recall" (1960); "Rutherford County and Its Hospital" (1960); and "A History of the North Carolina State Board of Health, 1877-1925" (1966).
For a full list of activities, organizations and honors, see "Who's Who in America," v. 27, 1952-1953, p. 2537.
Scope and Contents
The Benjamin E. Washburn papers contain few items of a personal nature. Consisting of reports, correspondence, scrapbooks, diaries, photographs, books and journals, the papers concern Washburn's employment with the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission (1913-1914) and the International Health Board/Division (1915-1939).
The papers focus on Dr. Washburn's Jamaica years. In addition to various reports and complete scrapbooks, they include correspondence regarding the Hookworm Campaign with the Jamaican Central Board of Health, The Rockefeller Foundation, and the United Fruit Company. Washburn's highly regarded venture in popular health education, the journal "Jamaica Public Health," is also among the Jamaica material.
After the transfer of the IHD Regional Headquarters for the Caribbean region from Kingston, Jamaica, to Havana, Cuba, in 1937, diaries required of Foundation staff are the only documentation of Dr. Washburn's professional activities.
Arrangement
The Benjamin E. Washburn papers are divided into four series:
Series 1 - Field Office Files
Series 2 - Scrapbooks
Series 3 - Miscellany
Series 1022 - Photographs
Related Materials
Nelson C. Davis Papers.
Public health; Jamaica; Trinidad; North Carolina; West Indies; Washburn, Benjamin Earle; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
- Field Office Files, 1916-1937; 1; 1.5 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the reports, correspondence, publications, memos, and diaries generated as a result of Dr. Washburn's employment with the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission and the International Health Board. The material is arranged geographically and chronologically in four subseries corresponding to Washburn's work in Trinidad, North Carolina, Jamaica, and the Caribbean region.
  Arrangement
  The material in this series is arranged geographically and chronologically in four subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Trinidad Subseries 2 - North Carolina Subseries 3 - Jamaica Subseries 4 - West Indies and Caribbean
  Each subseries is further arranged by type of record.
  - Field Office Files - Trinidad, 1
    This subseries is arranged by type of record.
    - Correspondence - Colonial Office, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Reports - Hookworm, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Reports - Hookworm, Alamance County, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Field Office Files - North Carolina, 2
    - Reports - Cooperative County Health Work, 1917-1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miscellany, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Field Office Files - Jamaica, 3
    The Jamaican files are grouped in several categories. The first, General, contains items which concern all aspects of IHB/D work on the island. Also included in this category are several Jamaican publications (1905-1938) on related subjects, such as mosquitos or vomiting sickness. Dealing with a particular tropical disease with which the IHB/D was active or considering involvement, the remaining Jamaican material is grouped under that malady -- Hookworm, Malaria, Tuberculosis, Yaws, and Yellow Fever.
    - General - Administrative Chart, 1925 (Box 1, Drawer 6)
    - General - Reports - Background, Health Work, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General - Reports - Cooperative Public Health Work, 1927, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General - Reports - Island Medical Department, 1929, 1932, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General - Reports - Island Medical Department, 1929, 1932, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General - Reports - Water Supply, Kingston & St. Andrew, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General - Publications - Jamaica Public Health, 1926-1935 (Box 2, Folder 12-19)
    - General - Publications - Bureau of Health Education, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - General - Publications - Miscellaneous, 1905-1938 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - General - Correspondence - Future of International Health Division (IHD) Work, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Hookworm - Correspondence, 1918-1928 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Hookworm - Reports - Infection Survey, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Hookworm - Reports - Relief and Control, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Hookworm - Reports - Campaign, 1919-1921 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - Hookworm - Reports - Commission, 1918-1926 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Hookworm - Reports - Commission, 1918-1926 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Hookworm - Miscellany, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Malaria - Survey and Correspondence, 1928-1932 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Tuberculosis - Reports and Correspondence, 1927-1933 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Yaws - Memorandum and Reports, 1932-1936 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Yellow Fever - Background Reports, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Field Office Files - West Indies and Caribbean, 4
    - Monthly Diaries, 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 36-38)
- Scrapbooks, 1916-1937; 2; 1.5 Cubic Feet
  The professional scrapbooks, covering the years 1916-1929 and 1932-1937, were kept by Dr. Washburn or a subordinate. They contain clippings from local newspapers in North Carolina and Jamaica and offer an almost daily record of Dr. Washburn and his staff. The personal scrapbooks, 1916?-1925 and 1931-1934, contain magazine and newspaper clippings on such subjects as North Carolina history, English royalty, and baldness. The scrapbooks are primarily bound volumes; in the early years they are fragments pieced together in approximate chronological order.
  The scrapbooks in this series are divided into professional and personal groupings, both of which are chronologically arranged.
  - North Carolina Public Health Work (Fragments), 1916-1919 (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
  - Jamaica Public Health Work (Fragments), 1921-1924 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Jamaica Public Health Work, 1925 - September 1927 (Box 5, Folder 42-44)
  - Jamaica Public Health Work, September 1927 - March 1933 (Box 6, Folder 45-47)
  - Jamaica Public Health Work, March 1933 - March 1935 (Box 7, Folder 48-50)
  - Jamaica Public Health Work, March 1935 - March 1935 (Box 8, Folder 51-52)
  - Personal, probably 1916-1925, 1931-1934 (Box 8, Folder 53-54)
- Miscellany, 1913-1960; 3; 0.5 Cubic Feet
  This series contains items not directly related to Washburn's career with Rockefeller-associated agencies. Included are a manuscript draft of his book "As I Recall," several articles by Washburn on such subjects as hiccups, book and class notes reflecting his health concerns, and items pertaining to Rutherford Hospital, Rutherfordton, North Carolina.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of record.
  - Family Tree, undated (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Manuscript Draft - "As I Recall", undated (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Notes - Class - London School of Hygiene & Tropical Medicine, 1929-1930 (Box 9, Folder 57-59)
  - Notes - Study, undated (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Reports and Correspondence - Rutherford Hospital, 1949-1959 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Writings, 1913-1960 (Box 9, Folder 62)
- Benjamin E. Washburn photographs, 1022; 8 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Subjects covered include local living conditions and customs, aspects of International Health Board/Division work, and scenic views.
  Arrangement note
  Photographs are arranged by geographical area:
  Trinidad North Carolina Jamaica West Indies Venezuela Surinam Dutch Guiana British Guiana
  Biographical / Historical
  A physician, public health officer, and author, Benjamin E. Washburn was born in Rutherford County, North Carolina, in 1885. Dr. Washburn received undergraduate (1906) and graduate (1909) degrees in English and history from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and graduated from the University of Virginia in 1911 with a degree in medicine. It was during his internship in Wilmington, North Carolina, that he met Zillah Howe, a nurse from Michigan, whom he married October 6, 1912.
  Following a brief private practice in Rutherford County, North Carolina, Dr. Washburn began his long connection with Rockefeller organizations as an employee of the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission. As field director for Haywood, Stanley, and Caswell counties in North Carolina, he led a hookworm eradication campaign; he later (May-December 1914) became a full-time health officer in Nash County, North Carolina, as part of a program of community sanitary work funded by The Rockefeller Foundation.
  In 1915 Dr. Washburn was appointed field director for the International Health Commission's campaign for control of hookworm in British Guiana and Trinidad. Returning to North Carolina in 1916, Washburn, as county health officer in Wilson County, developed a program of health work intended to serve as a model for other counties and as a training center for International Health Board field staff. In 1917, Dr. Washburn was appointed director of the new state Bureau of County Health Work where he was responsible for the creation of cooperative health programs in ten North Carolina counties.
  Dr. Washburn left North Carolina again in 1930 to direct the IHB's Hookworm Campaign in Jamaica and remained to inaugurate and oversee the Malaria Campaign, the Tuberculosis Commission, and the Bureau of Health Education. In 1935, he was appointed regional director for the International Health Division in the West Indies and Central America. Washburn retired from The Rockefeller Foundation in 1939.
  Upon retirement, Washburn returned to Rutherfordton, North Carolina, where he was active in state and local public health affairs. He also served as health editor for the Raleigh, North Carolina, "Progressive Farmer" from 1940 to 1951 and wrote several books devoted to his health interests.
  Dr. Washburn is the author of "Jamaica Health Stories and Plays" (1929); "The Health Game" (1930); "A Country Doctor in the South Mountains" (1955); "As I Recall" (1960); "Rutherford County and Its Hospital" (1960); and "A History of the North Carolina State Board of Health, 1877-1925" (1966).
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  Collection is open for scholarly research. Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
  Washburn, Benjamin Earle
  - Jamaica, Mounted on board, captions on back, some fading, 1 unmounted (Box 7, Folder 70)
    Hookworm, diseases, doctors, Jamaica Staff, yaws.
  - Miscellaneous, Mounted on board, captions on back, some staining, 2 unmounted (Box 7, Folder 71)
    Jamaica Staff, public health, privys, sanitation.
  - South America, Mounted on board, captions on back, some fading, staining (Box 8, Folder 72)
    Diseases, malaria, spraying, incubators, Paris Green, drainage ditches, privys, health officials, staff.
  - South America, Mounted on board, captions on back, some fading (Box 8, Folder 73)
    Diseases, malaria, spraying, Paris Green, drainage ditches, health officers.
  - Trinidad, Mounted on paper, mounts badly stained, prints faded, stained, yellowing, creased, torn (Box 8, Folder 74)
    Diseases, leprosy, yaws, hookworm, elephantitis, privys, housing, living conditions, Hinduism.
  - North Carolina - Cooperative Health Work, 1916-1917; Mounted on thin paper, embrittled, heavy silvering, losses, staining, fading, (Box 8, Folder 75)
    County buildings, privys, homes, India, religious monuments, parades, diseases, elephantitis.
  - Jamaica - Hookworm Campaign and Staff, 1920-1923; Mounted on paper, badly embrittled, heavy silvering, yellowing, fading, severe adhesive staining (Box 8, Folder 76)
    Health officers, diseases, hookworm, leprosy, Jamaica staff, privys, houses, drainage ditches.
  - Miscellaneous Countries, c. 1915; Mounted on paper, badly embrittled, heavy silvering, staining, fading, yellowing (Box 8, Folder 77)
    West Indies, Venezuela, Surinam, Dutch Guiana, British Guiana. Landscapes, seascapes, travel, houses, towns, diseases, leprosy, indigenous peoples.